"Is Aging a Disease?"
For decades, one of the most
contested questions
in gerontology has been
whether or not aging itself
should be considered a disease.
But aging is natural,
the counterargument goes,
so it can't be a disease.
Yes, but so is getting
an infection,
and we call that a disease.
But aging is universal.
Yes, but everybody
gets the common cold, too.
If you ask people
whether they think
a variety of conditions
should be
classified as diseases,
you get an odd mix.
For example, alcohol dependence
is considered a disease,
but nicotine dependence is not.
Interestingly,
the lay public is more likely
to view aging as a disease
than doctors,
despite medicine's
historical penchant
to medicalize everything.
Who could forget drapetomania,
the mental "illness"
afflicting slaves
who escaped plantations.
Masturbation
was considered a disease,
complete with
grizzly surgical solutions.
Homosexuality was
officially labeled a disease
within my lifetime,
yet medicine is hesitant
to label aging an ailment.
What does it matter
what we call it?
A rose by any other name
wilts just as fast.
The hope is that
disease classification
would lead to
greater resource allocation
for aging research,
just as the recent declaration
of obesity as a disease did
for obesity research.
Aging is arguably
one of the most important
unsolved problems of humanity,
yet less than 0.1 percent
of the National Institutes
of Health budget
is spent on understanding
the aging process.
Even though aging
may be the leading cause
of disease and death,
only 4 out of 14
general medicine textbooks
have a chapter on the subject,
and 5 of 14 didn't appear
to address aging at all.
The science of aging
appears to have been
"relegated to a limbo
reserved for
impractical projects
or eccentric whims
not quite worthy
of serious
scientific consideration.”
Why doesn't Big Pharma invest
in what would certainly be
a blockbuster drug?
Why spend the money on research
when it can be spent
marketing all the unproven
anti-aging products
they already sell?
Many of the leading lines
of dietary supplements
are owned by drug companies.
They're the ones selling
"cosmeceuticals"
and "age reverse" skin creams.
Drug maker Sanofi even partnered
with Coca-Cola
to come up with
a "beauty drink."
They're already making money
hand over fist
preying on the public's
gullibility and desperation
for anti-aging products.
Why waste valuable
marketing money
on proving anything
actually works?